so featurelength okay we're really and
right one of the questions she's asking
is what do you think the importance of
fungi is at this point well I think
fungi is a critically important at this
stage in the evolution of life on this
planet simply for the fact that we look
at evolutionary history
we know there's been at least two major
extinction events after which fungi
inherited the earth
250 million years ago there was a
greatest extinction more than 90% of the
species in the fossil record disappeared
suddenly and there's three theories one
the methane hydrate burst out of the
oceans volcanoes in Siberia or an
asteroid impact I don't see them as
mutually exclusive the asteroid impact
could have triggered the volcanoes and
the methane hydrate outburst but in any
event the earth became strident rather
than dust
there's a massive die-off of species and
those organisms that associated with
fungi survived so fungi inherited the
earth 250 million years ago after this
big extinction event then 65 million
years ago we had another extinction of
that the asteroid impact we know hit the
earth and the earth was shrouded in dust
and the ratio of pollen to fungal spores
at the Pitti boundary of the
permian-triassic boundary was 10 to 1
and directly after that event there were
no pollen spores for hundreds of years
thousands of years all fungal spores so
we know that there's two extinction
events the lesson and the evolution of
life on this planet those organs that
paired with fungi survived extinction
events now we're in 6x the greatest
extinction event seen since then and by
reports though it's a thousand times
more severe number one because we have
more species but we're losing thousand
times more species than they there seems
to have done previously in history so we
live in our lifetimes we think
everything's fine and you know the grass
is green the air is clean everything is
fine but in geological time this is just
a small blip
and when we look at the degradation of
habitats we're in the middle of an
extinction event that we can't even see
or comprehend we're losing more species
than can even determine that there are
and there's more species in the ground
that we haven't identified than there
are that we've identified by orders of
magnitude
so as the ecosystems unravel and we read
benefit here from being a having a
plurality of microorganisms that sustain
us and so I maybe Paul Stamets speaking
with one voice but I'm a community of
microbes unified together as an organism
living in symbiosis but not only within
my own body but in contact with all the
microbes around me and as we lose
species in the ecosystem is like losing
rivers an airplane at what point will we
have so much loss of biodiversity we'll
have catastrophic failure and I think
we're right in the middle of that
catastrophic failure emerging right now
people talk about tipping points and the
concern that I think a lot of us who
have knowledge bases and our specialties
that are now collaborating and sharing
information is that this tipping point
is really moving us very very quickly
towards a massive ecological failure and
as we have failure of the food chains
which fungi sustain as we have diseases
and poverty and terrorism then the
immune system of the habitats is
impugned as well as the individuals
living within it and disease vectors
will proliferate and there's one lesson
of nature is that if any organism
exceeds the carrying capacity of this
ecosystem the ecosystem revolts against
it and we have extinction events so we
are at the point right now that if we
don't wake up and engage microorganisms
as to our allies and intelligently work
with them then they will seek revenge
against us I think that's just the way
of the balance of nature and organisms
and 99% of all species and the evolution
of life has plan have become an extinct
so that's an extinction is a normal
consequence of life now we're conscious
of that perhaps more so than other
organisms or debatably some people could
say we're not conscious of that but I
think we're very quickly moving on a
slippery slope you know and so this is a
concern that I have in terms of
sustainability sustainability has to
engage micro organisms especially fungi
that build the food web of life and if
we don't
invest in them then they will divest of
us one of the the ultimate aims of the